If you're a sports fan, you may be familiar with the emotional rollercoaster that comes with sports spectatorship.
如果你是体育迷，你可能熟悉体育观赛带来的情绪过山车。
Whether you're part of a buzzing crowd in a stadium, or just watching at home on TV, it's easy to get caught up in the highs and the lows when you celebrate or commiserate with your favourite team or athlete.
无论你是置身于体育场内喧闹的人群中，还是仅仅在家看电视，当你为你最喜欢的球队或运动员庆祝或惋惜时，很容易沉浸在情绪的高峰和低谷之中。
Those feelings are so strong, in fact, that a study from Croatia, published in PubMed, showed that the emotional stress during a football match increased the risk of a cardiovascular incident.
克罗地亚一项发表在PubMed上的研究表明，这些情绪事实上非常强烈，以至于足球比赛期间的情绪压力增加了发生心血管意外的风险。
But can watching sports be good for you too?
但观看体育比赛对你也有好处吗？
The evidence suggests that people who watch live sporting events experience greater wellbeing than those who don't.
有证据表明，观看现场体育赛事的人比不观看的人体验到更高的幸福感。
A study published in Frontiers in Public Health by the Anglia Ruskin University in the UK, found sports spectators felt less lonely and had higher scores for life satisfaction.
英国安格利亚鲁金斯大学发表在《公共卫生前沿》上的一项研究发现，体育观众感到不那么孤独，生活满意度得分也更高。
Lead author Helen Keys said in a press release, "watching live sport of all types provides many opportunities for social interaction and this helps to forge group identity and belonging."
主要作者海伦·凯斯在一份新闻稿中说："观看各种类型的现场体育比赛提供了许多社交互动的机会，这有助于形成群体认同感和归属感。"
She says this then reduces loneliness and boosts wellbeing.
她说，这反过来又减少了孤独感，提升了幸福感。
But, if for any reason you aren't keen on going to live events, don't worry!
但是，无论什么原因，如果你不喜欢去现场观看比赛，也别担心！
Watching sports on TV or on the internet may also have positive effects, according to a 2021 study by Tsuji and colleagues.
根据辻及其同事2021年的一项研究，在电视或互联网上观看体育比赛也可能产生积极影响。
They found that older adults who watched sports were less likely to have depressive symptoms than those who didn't.
他们发现，观看体育比赛的老年人比不观看的老年人出现抑郁症状的可能性更低。
On top of that, the sports spectators tended to have richer social networks than non-spectators.
除此之外，体育观众往往比非观众拥有更丰富的社交网络。
The authors suggest that the social networks you gain through watching sports may lower the risk of depressive symptoms.
作者认为，通过观看体育比赛获得的社交网络可能会降低抑郁症状的风险。
So, the cheers at a live sports event or even casual chit-chat with friends about your favourite team can bring a sense of camaraderie and may reduce loneliness and depression.
所以，在现场体育赛事中的欢呼，甚至与朋友闲聊你最喜欢的球队，都能带来一种同志情谊，并可能减少孤独感和抑郁。
It seems the health benefits of sports are not limited to physical activity through participation in them, but that we can make gains in our general wellbeing through social bonding.
体育对健康的益处似乎不仅限于通过参与其中进行身体活动，我们还可以通过社交联系来提升整体幸福感。